Guide to the Robert S. Smith Papers, 1947-1982 and undated RL.01219
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Robert S. Smith papers
1947-1982 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Smith, Robert S. (Robert Sidney), 1904-1969
RL.01219
16.5 Linear Feet
Robert S. Smith is a retired executive who worked as an art director for a number of advertising agencies including William H. Weintraub and Co.; Norman Craig and Kummel; and Ogilvy & Mather (O&M). The Robert S. Smith Papers span the years 1947 through 1982 and document Smith's work as an art director for several advertising agencies, including Norman Craig and Kummel; and Ogilvy & Mather (O&M). The materials consist primarily of sketches; paintings; photographs and contact sheets; advertising layouts and proofs; storyboards for television commercials; and house advertisements for O&M. Clients include Consolidated Cigar (El Producto and La Palina brands); Diageo (Gilbey's liquors), DuBonnet; General Foods (Maxim coffee, Gaines dog food); IBM; Maidenform; Mars; Nabisco; Rand McNally; Ronson; Schenley Distillers (Melrose liquors); and Toro. Also included are a set of sketches and drawings, some signed, by the artist Paul Rand. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
1200 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Robert S. Smith Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2000.
Biographical Note
Robert S. Smith served as Art Director for several advertising agencies, including: William H. Weintraub and Co.; Norman Craig and Kummel; Ogilvy & Mather (O&M); Fletcher Richards; and Calkins and Holden. He designed advertisements for National Distillers, U.S. Rubber, Revlon, Ronson, Rand McNally, Newsweek, and Consolidated Cigar Corporation, among others. He also served on the Board of Directors for the Morris Junior Museum, preparing brochures, posters and slides for lectures; photographs for exhibits; and a public relations film strip. He was also an active member of the Art Director's Club of New York. An avid photographer, Smith's photographs were published by Gilbey's, IBM, the National Guard, Folkways Records. He was once awarded third prize in a New York World-Telegram & Sun child photography contest.
Collection Overview
The Robert S. Smith Papers span the years 1947 through 1982 and document Smith's work as a commercial artist and art director for several advertising agencies, including Norman Craig and Kummel; and Ogilvy & Mather (O&M). The materials consist primarily of sketches; paintings; photographs and contact sheets; advertising layouts and proofs; storyboards for television commercials; and house advertisements for O&M. Clients include Consolidated Cigar (El Producto and La Palina brands); Diageo (Gilbey's liquors), DuBonnet; General Foods (Maxim coffee, Gaines dog food); IBM; Maidenform; Mars; Nabisco; Rand McNally; Ronson; Schenley Distillers (Melrose liquors); and Toro. Also included are a set of sketches, paintings and drawings, some signed, by the artist Paul Rand.
Collection Arrangement
Materials are arranged into four series by size: Small Format, Medium Format, Large Format and Extra Large Format. Within these series, items were grouped into subseries by genre: Brochures, Photographs, Proofs and Tearsheets, Sketches and Miscellaneous. Brochures include booklet-style advertistements. Photographs include photographs and contact sheets for several campaigns, including Milky Way and Gilbey's (Gin and Vodka). Proofs and Tearsheets include advertising proofs intended for publication in newspapers and magazines, as well as magazine and newspaper tearsheets and photostats. Items were separated into glossy and newsprint materials. Sketches include pencil, charcoal and pastel drawings for ad campaigns, as well as collages of glued paper items.
Related Material
Related materials may be found in the following Hartman Center collections: the Anthony Weir Papers; the Bates Worldwide Inc. Records; the Garrett Orr Papers; the Gene Federico Papers; the Howard Scott Papers; the Lore Parker Papers; and the William E. Phillips Papers.
Sketches; Storyboards; Photographs; Contact sheets; Institutional advertising -- United States; Commercial art -- United States; Advertising -- United States; Advertising -- Liquor industry; Advertising -- Cigars; Advertising layout and typography -- United States; Advertising photography -- United States; Advertising, art in.; Toro Company; Schenley Distillers Company; Ronson Corporation; Ogilvy & Mather; Nabisco, Inc.; Rand, Paul, 1914-1996; Rand McNally and Company; Maidenform (New York, N.Y.); Mars, Incorporated; International Business Machines Corporation; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; Smith, Robert S. (Robert Sidney), 1904-1969; DuBonnet (Firm); Smith, Robert S. (Robert Sidney), 1904-1969; General Foods Corporation; Consolidated Cigar Corporation; Diageo (Firm)
- Small format, 1956-1977 and undated, 1 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes proofs, storyboards, tearsheets and photographs, as well as miscellaneous office correspondence between O&M employees. Items organized by genre and ordered alphabetically.
  - General (Box 1)
    - Biographical sketch, undated (Box 1)
    - Christmas greeting card, undated (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 1956 and undated (Box 1)
    - Packaging, Bliss home permanent, undated (Box 1)
    - Printed material, Type Talks, 1956 (Box 1)
  - Photographs
    - Unidentified campaign, undated (Box 1)
  - Proofs and Tear Sheets
    - IBM, 1965 (Box 1)
    - Inco, undated (Box 1)
    - Lovera cigars, undated (Box 1)
    - Melrose bourbon, undated (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous deodorants (includes Veto, Odalin, Colgate, Suppress), undated (Box 1)
    - Rand McNally, undated (Box 1)
    - Ronson razors and lighters, undated (Box 1)
    - Samovar vodka, undated (Box 1)
    - Silky home permanent, undated (Box 1)
    - WBBM-TV, undated (Box 1)
  - Sketches
    - El Producto, undated (Box 1)
  - Storyboards
    - American Express, 1975 and undated (Box 1)
    - Gaines, undated (Box 1)
    - General Foods, 1966-1977 and undated (Box 1)
    - Lever Brothers, 1966 and undated (Box 1)
    - Mars, Inc., undated (Box 1)
    - Nabisco, 1974-1975 and undated (Box 1)
    - Prolamine, diet pills, 1965 (Box 1)
    - Puerto Rico, 1977 and undated (Box 1)
    - Toro, snowpup, undated (Box 1)
- Medium Format, 1947-1979 and undated, 3 boxes
  Includes glossy and newsprint proofs and tearsheets, photographs, advertising sketches, as well as color sketches by Paul Rand. Items arranged by genre and ordered alphabetically.
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Lester Robbins Associates, holiday greeting, undated (Box 2)
    - Paul Rand sketches, undated (Box 2)
  - Photographs
    - Gilbey's, undated (Box 2)
    - Unidentified campaign, undated (Box 2)
  - Proofs and Tear Sheets
    - Glossy
      - Alka Seltzer, 1977 (Box 2)
      - American Express, 1978, 1980 (Box 2)
      - Ancient Age bourbon, 1948-1951 (Box 2)
      - Bliss home permanent, 1957 and undated (Box 2)
      - Burns Security Services, 1959 (Box 2)
      - Chanel, 1956 (Box 2)
      - Cinzano vermouth, 1963 (Box 2)
      - Coronet liquor, 1948 and undated (Box 2)
      - DuBonnet liquor, undated (Box 2)
      - DuBouchett liquor, 1956-1957 (Box 2)
      - El Producto, 1953-1956 (Box 2)
      - Gaines, Full Course dog food, 1978 (Box 2)
      - Gibson, Diamond Eight whiskey, 1950 (Box 2)
      - Gilbey's, 1958-1963 and undated (Box 2)
      - Good Seasons, 1964-1965 (Box 2)
      - IBM, undated (Box 2)
      - James Pepper whiskey, 1953-1954 (Box 2)
      - Kaufmann's, undated (Box 2)
      - Kentucky bourbon, 1960 (Box 2)
      - King George whiskey and scotch, 1959-1960 (Box 2)
      - La Palina cigars, 1953-1956 (Box 2)
      - Mars Corporation, 1968 (Box 3)
      - Maidenform, 1956-1957 (Box 3)
      - Maxwell House, undated (Box 3)
      - Nabisco, 1974 (Box 3)
      - Newsweek, 1960-1961 (Box 3)
      - Pepperidge Farm, 1970 and undated (Box 3)
      - Puerto Rico, undated (Box 3)
      - Puppy Palace, 1968-1969 (Box 3)
      - Rand McNally, 1959-1960 and undated (Box 3)
      - Revlon, 1955-1956 (Box 3)
      - Ronson lighters and razors, 1956-1957 (Box 3)
      - Sportsman lotion, 1956 (Box 3)
      - Stafford clothing, 1947-1948 (Box 3)
      - Steuben Glass, 1978 (Box 3)
      - Vat 69, 1960-1961 and undated (Box 3)
      - Veto deodorant, 1957 (Box 3)
      - World Wildlife Federation, 1979 and undated (Box 3)
    - Newsprint
      - DuBonnet liquor, 1947-1948 (Box 3)
      - El Producto cigars, undated (Box 3)
      - Gilbey's, 1958 and undated (Box 3)
      - James Pepper whiskey, 1952 and undated (Box 3)
      - Robeson cutlery, 1948 (Box 3)
      - Stafford clothing, 1948 (Box 3)
  - Sketches (Box 4)
    - Airwick, undated (Box 4)
    - Ancient Age bourbon, undated (Box 4)
    - Chanel, undated (Box 4)
    - Conmar Zippers, undated (Box 4)
    - Crown Jewel perfume, undated (Box 4)
    - Lovera cigars, undated (Box 4)
    - Maxim coffee, undated (Box 4)
    - Melrose gin, undated (Box 4)
    - Rand McNally, undated (Box 4)
    - Revlon, undated (Box 4)
    - Robeson cutlery, undated (Box 4)
    - Stradivari, undated (Box 4)
- Large format 1953-1982 and undated, 8 boxes
  Includes proofs, tearsheets, sketches and brochures for primarily liquor, cosmetics and clothing campaigns. Also includes two of Paul Rand's color sketches, and a printed poster designed by Rand for Interfaith Day. Also includes proofs for undated O&M house advertisements. Items organized by genre and arranged alphabetically by folder title. Matted proofs and sketches were boxed separately from unmatted items.
  - Brochures (Box 5)
    - El Producto cigars, undated (Box 5)
    - Gilbey's, 1963 (Box 5)
    - Melrose whiskey, 1958 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Paul Rand Interfaith Day poster, undated (Box 5)
    - Paul Rand sketches, undated (Box 5)
  - Photographs
    - Gilbey's, undated (Box 5)
    - Milky Way contact sheets, undated (Box 5)
    - Puppy Palace, undated (Box 5)
  - Proofs and Tear Sheets (Box 6)
    - Ammens Powder, 1964 (Box 6)
    - Conmar Zippers, undated (Box 6)
    - DuBarry cosmetics, 1957 (Box 6)
    - El Producto cigars, 1955 (Box 6)
    - Gilbey's, 1959-1963 (Box 6)
    - Hill and Hill liquor, 1962 (Box 6)
    - Inco, 1965, 1979 and undated (Box 6)
    - International Paper Company, 1977 (Box 6)
    - Jeep, 1956-1957 (Box 6)
    - La Palina cigars, 1953 (Box 6)
    - Maidenform, undated (Box 6)
    - Marriott, 1980 and undated (Box 6)
    - National Distillers, 1960-1963 (Box 6)
    - O&M, undated (Box 6)
    - Peugeot, 1981-1982 (Box 6)
    - Puerto Rico, 1976 and undated (Box 6)
    - Revlon, 1955-1956 (Box 6)
    - Robeson cutlery, 1950 and undated (Box 6)
    - Scientific American, undated (Box 6)
    - Toro lawnmowers, 1972-1973 (Box 6)
  - Matted Proofs and Sketches (Box 7)
    - Gilbey's, undated (Box 7)
    - Gilbey's (continued), undated (Box 8)
    - Gilbey's (continued), undated (Box 9)
    - Gilbey's (continued), undated (Box 10)
    - Gilbey's (continued), undated (Box 10a)
    - Cinzano liquor, undated (Box 11)
    - Hershey's chocolate, undated (Box 11)
    - Hill and Hill liquor, undated (Box 11)
    - IBM, undated (Box 11)
    - Kentucky Colonel bourbon, undated (Box 12)
    - Ronson razors and lighters, undated (Box 12)
    - Unidentified campaign, undated (Box 12)
    - Vat 69 liquor, undated (Box 12)
  - Sketches
    - Bourbon Deluxe, undated (Box 12)
    - Coronet Brandy, undated (Box 12)
    - Crème Wash, undated (Box 12)
    - Driven Snow, undated (Box 12)
    - DuBonnet liquor, undated (Box 12)
    - El Producto cigars, undated (Box 12)
    - Gilbey's, undated (Box 13)
    - La Palina cigars, undated (Box 13)
    - Ronson lighters and razors, undated (Box 13)
    - Samovar liquor, undated (Box 13)
    - Snow Crop, undated (Box 13)
  - Storyboards
    - Lever Brothers, 1969 (Box 13)
- Extra Large Format, 1961-1979, 2 Boxes and 1 oversize folder
  Includes proofs, tearsheets and sketches. Items organized by genre and arranged alphabetically. Clients include Newsweek magazine, IBM, DuBarry cosmetics, Revlon, Gilbey's (Gin and Vodka), and Hill and Hill liquor.
  - Proofs and Tear Sheets (Box 14)
    - Glossy
      - IBM, 1964-1965 (Box 14)
      - Maxim coffee, 1964-1965 (Box 14)
      - Newsweek, 1960-1961 (Box 14)
      - Puerto Rico, 1975-1979 (Box 14)
    - Newsprint
      - Newsweek, 1961 (Box 14)
  - Sketches
    - DuBarry cosmetics, undated (Box 14)
    - Gilbey's, undated (Box 14)
    - Hill and Hill liquor, undated, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Revlon, undated (Box 15)
    - Toro lawnmowers, undated (Box 15)
  - Gilby's Gin sketches (Oversize-folder 1)